<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--
Licensed to the Apache Software Foundation (ASF) under one or more
contributor license agreements.  See the NOTICE file distributed with
this work for additional information regarding copyright ownership.
The ASF licenses this file to You under the Apache License, Version 2.0
(the "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with
the License.  You may obtain a copy of the License at

     http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
limitations under the License.
-->
<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Home</title>
  <author email="dev@commons.apache.org">Commons Documentation Team</author>
 </properties>
<body>
<!-- ================================================== -->
<section name="Commons Text">

<p>
Apache Commons Text is a library focused on algorithms working on strings.
</p>

</section>
<!-- ================================================== -->
<section name="Documentation">
<p>
We provide documentation in the form of a <a href="userguide.html">User Guide</a>, 
<a href="javadocs/api-release/index.html">Javadoc</a>, and <a href="project-reports.html">Project Reports</a>.
</p>
<p>
The <a href="scm.html">Git repository</a> can be
<a href="https://gitbox.apache.org/repos/asf?p=commons-text.git">browsed</a>, or you can browse/contribute via <a href="https://github.com/apache/commons-text">GitHub</a>.
</p>
</section>
<!-- ================================================== -->
<section name="Security">
  <subsection name="CVE-2022-42889 prior to 1.10.0, RCE when applied to untrusted input">
    <p>
    On 2022-10-13, the Apache Commons Text team disclosed <a href="https://www.cve.org/CVERecord?id=CVE-2022-42889">CVE-2022-42889</a>. Key takeaways:
    <ul>
      <li>If you rely on software that uses a version of commons-text prior to 1.10.0, you are likely still not vulnerable: only if this software uses the <code>StringSubstitutor</code> API without properly sanitizing any untrusted input.</li>
      <li>If your own software uses commons-text, double-check whether it uses the <code>StringSubstitutor</code> API without properly sanitizing any untrusted input. If so, an update to 1.10.0 could be a quick workaround, but the recommended solution is to also properly validate and sanitize any untrusted input.</li>
    </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
    Apache Commons Text is a low-level library for performing various text operations, such as escaping, calculating string differences, and substituting placeholders in the text with values looked up through interpolators. When using the string substitution feature, some of the available interpolators can trigger network access or code execution. This is intended, but it also means an application that includes user input in the string passed to the substitution without properly sanitizing it would allow an attacker to trigger those interpolators.
    </p>
    <p>For that reason the Apache Commons Text team have decided to update the configuration to be more "secure by default", so that the impact of a failure to validate inputs is mitigated and will not give an attacker access to these interpolators. However, it is still recommended that users treat untrusted input with care.
    </p>
    <p>
    We're not currently aware of any applications that pass untrusted input to the substitutor and thus would have been impacted by this problem prior to Apache Commons Text 1.10.0.
    </p>
    <p>
    This issue is different from <a href="https://logging.apache.org/log4j/2.x/security.html#log4j-2.15.0">Log4Shell (CVE-2021-44228)</a> because in Log4Shell, string interpolation was possible from the log message body, which commonly contains untrusted input. In the Apache Common Text issue, the relevant method is explicitly intended and clearly documented to perform string interpolation, so it is much less likely that applications would inadvertently pass in untrusted input without proper validation.
    </p>
    <p>
    Credit: this issue was reported independently by Ruilin and by <a href="https://github.com/pwntester">@pwntester (Alvaro Muñoz)</a> of the <a href="https://securitylab.github.com">GitHub Security Lab team</a>. Thank you!
    </p>
    <p>
    References:
    <ul>
    <li><a href="https://lists.apache.org/thread/n2bd4vdsgkqh2tm14l1wyc3jyol7s1om">Announcement on dev@commons.apache.org</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://www.openwall.com/lists/oss-security/2022/10/13/4">Announcement on oss-security</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://cve.mitre.org/cgi-bin/cvename.cgi?name=CVE-2022-42889">Advisory on cve.org</a></li>
    <li><a href="https://securitylab.github.com/advisories/GHSL-2022-018_Apache_Commons_Text/">GHSL advisory</a></li>
    </ul>
    </p>
  </subsection>
</section>
<!-- ================================================== -->
<section name="Release Information">
<p>
  Download the latest release from dependency-info.html</p>
<p>
  Alternatively, you can use a <a href="dependency-info.html">build tool dependency</a>.
</p>

 <p>
  For information on previous releases see the <a href="changes-report.html">Release History</a>, and to download previous releases see the <a href="https://archive.apache.org/dist/commons/text/">Commons Text Archive</a>.
 </p>

</section>
<!-- ================================================== -->
<section name="Getting Involved">
<p>
The <a href="mail-lists.html">commons developer mailing list</a> is the main channel of communication for contributors. Please remember that the lists are shared between all commons components, so prefix your email by [text]. </p>
<p>You can also visit the #apache-commons IRC channel on irc.freenode.net or peruse <a href="issue-tracking.html">JIRA</a>. Specific links of interest for JIRA are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Ideas looking for code: <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/issues/?jql=project%20%3D%20TEXT%20AND%20resolution%20%3D%20Unresolved%20AND%20fixVersion%20%3D%20%22Patch%20Needed%22%20ORDER%20BY%20priority%20DESC">Patch Needed</a></li>
<li>Issues with patches, looking for reviews: <a href="https://issues.apache.org/jira/issues/?jql=fixVersion%20%3D%20%22Review%20Patch%22%20AND%20project%20%3D%20TEXT%20AND%20resolution%20%3D%20Unresolved%20ORDER%20BY%20priority%20DESC">Review Patch</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Alternatively you can go through the <em>Needs Work</em> tags in the <a href="taglist.html">TagList report</a>.</p>
<p>If you'd like to offer up pull requests via GitHub rather than applying patches to JIRA, we have a <a href="https://github.com/apache/commons-text/">GitHub mirror</a>. </p>
</section>
<!-- ================================================== -->
<section name="Support">
<p>
The <a href="mail-lists.html">commons mailing lists</a> act as the main support forum.
The user list is suitable for most library usage queries.
The dev list is intended for the development discussion.
Please remember that the lists are shared between all commons components,
so prefix your email by [text].
</p>
<p>
Bug reports and enhancements are also welcomed via the <a href="issue-tracking.html">JIRA</a> issue tracker.
Please read the instructions carefully.
</p>
</section>
<!-- ================================================== -->
</body>
</document>
